Kyle Batson UX/UI Designer

Profile

Senior UX designer working to improve the experience of products and services and making a positive impact on the lives of those my designs impact. I take a holistic approach to understanding how systems work at a high-level, but also have extensive experience of getting down into the smallest details of interactions that work together to delight users. I am passionate about the quality of the products I work on and advocate for the needs of the user in every stage of product development. I have extensive experience in front-end development and accessibility and I am a strong advocate for user-centered design at an organizational level. I have also led software engineering teams so I am proficient at communicating about the design process, and generating empathy towards users.

Experience

2018-now |

America's Job Link Alliance - Topeka, KS

Senior UX/UI Designer

- » Redesigned and implemented the front-end of a rebuilt workforce job board and content management application focused on accessibility and usability used in 9 states.
- » Drove research activities traveling to job center sites in 5 states to observe user behavior, and interview users about their backgrounds and needs in order to derive insights about users and how site features could be improved.
- » Utilized user research, competitive analysis, and usability best practices to design new product features to help meet user goals by addressing gaps in functionality.
- » Used research to develop personas and communicate back to management and stakeholders pain points and areas for improvement.
- » Created a responsive and mobile-first design to ensure clear usability across mobile and desktop devices.
- » Generated a UI toolkit and style guide as a pattern library defining the logic and behavior of interactive components. These artifacts were used by designers and software engineers across multiple products to ensure consistency of design and usability.
- » Implemented user interface design in a Ruby on Rails app through use of semantic HTML5 markup, CSS3/SASS, and Javascript along with the Zurb Foundation front-end library.
- » Utilized BrowserStack and Oracle VirtualBox to ensure compatibility and consistency across multiple operating systems and browsers.
- » Performed accessibility analysis of multiple applications on a page by page basis using VoiceOver, axe DevTools, ARC Toolkit, and WCAG Color contrast checker.
- » Created semantic HTML, ARIA tagging to conform the application WCAG 2.1 AA conformance.
- » Performed user interviews to better understand user needs and evaluate usability pain points.
- » Balanced federal reporting requirements with usability best practices to provide solutions that would both promote quality user experiences and support regulatory conformance.
- » Generated high-level product strategy and helped create a product roadmap to implement that strategy step-by-step.
- » Facilitated design discussions to create solutions with cross-functional teams.
- » Advocated a user-centered design philosophy and coached team members and leadership how to integrate lessons from design thinking in the broader software development life cycle.
- » Fostered empathy towards users throughout the organization to ensure that user experience was always considered in determining priorities and resource allocation.
- » Created presentations and attended annual conferences communicating user research and insights to non-designers and non-technical staff.
- » Created interactive prototypes to communicate design decisions and facilitate brainstorming and feedback from product management and technical staff.

2015-2017 | Educational Testing Service - Lawrence, KS

UX Design Team Manager - 07/2015 to 11/2017

- » In addition to continuing my previous role as a Software Development Team Lead, I was also promoted to the role of Design Team Manager.
- » Directed consistent, evidence-based user-centered design approaches for a suite of enterprise-level web applications that delivered over 6 million assessments across 3 states.
- » Managed a team of three UX designers and an accessibility specialist.
- » Formalized design processes in an Agile Scrum workflow to integrate with software developers, project managers, QA staff, and stakeholders.
- » Utilized my technical knowledge and interpersonal skills to mediate conflict and disagreements between staff, and to foster communication and understanding between teams.
- » Utilized competitive analysis, user feedback, and usability best practices to design new workflows and features.
- » Facilitated design discussions to create solutions with cross-functional teams.
- » Utilized design research to design new product features and to help meet user goals by addressing gaps in functionality.
- » Utilized user research to facilitate the creation of personas and journey maps to better communicate opportunities to improve the user experience of products.
- » Provided feedback and critique to designers dedicated to different application components.
- » Mentored and coached team members to improve their design skill set.
- » Advocated for universal design principles to ensure that accessibility was considered at every stage of the SDLC.

2013-2015 | Educational Testing Service/Computerized Assessments & Learning - Lawrence, KS

Software Developer Team Lead

I started the role as part of Computerized Assessments & Learning (CA&L) but the company was acquired and integrated into ETS where I maintained the same role.

- » Managed team of 7 front-end developers, their development priorities, agile sprint assignments, and workloads.
- » Triaged issues as primary point of contact across the application delivery system.
- » Continued to design and generate requirements for user interface and interaction design for a complex user-facing enterprise assessment application.
- » Performed user testing to better understand how users interacted with the application and understood its tools.
- » Created improved workflows and features based on user feedback and implementation of best practices.
- » Ensure code was modular, configurable, robust, reliable and consistent in style.
- » Performed code reviews and mentored junior developers and interns.
- » Generated high-level product strategy and helped create a product roadmap to implement that strategy step-by-step.
- » Worked with upper-management, project managers, and other stakeholders to manage and assign team resources, priorities, workload, and sprints.
- » Worked with several accessibility specialists to ensure all application features met with Section 508 accessibility standards and best practices.
- » Created interface and interaction design requirements for custom assessment tools such as text-to-speech controls, text highlighting, drawing on screen, sticky notes, and more.
- » Ensured all tools and inputs were fully accessible for keyboard navigation and screen reader users.
- » Performed analysis and worked with API ingestion team to generate parsing rules to convert XML assessment questions into a consumable, modular JSON format.
- » Documented system functionality and requirements in Confluence for consumption of cross-functional and non-technical teams including documentation writers.

2011-2013 | Computerized Assessments & Learning - Lawrence, KS

Interaction Designer

- » Worked with stakeholders and psychometricians to create multiple, configurable user interface styles for a single enterprise assessment application.
- » Designed and created innovative "technology enhanced" assessment items to evaluate student knowledge.
- » Created standards-based, semantic front-end templates to implement designs consistently across a multitude of different browsers and operating systems.
- » Performed user testing to better understand how users interacted with the application and understood its tools.
- » Created improved workflows and features based on user feedback and implementation of best practices.
- » Created interface and interaction design logic and behavior requirements for custom assessment tools including text highlighting, drawing on screen, and sticky notes and ensured compatibility with mouse, keyboard, and touch

interactions.

- Created interface and interaction design requirements for custom assessment question types such as drag-and-drop, reorder, text editing, fill-in-the-blanks, audio playback and recording, etc.
- Ensured all tools and inputs were fully accessible for keyboard navigation and screen reader users.
- Created interaction requirements for a custom Javascript-based text editor with features such as custom caret positioning between lines, custom spell-checker, mobile and desktop text highlighting with cut, copy, and paste features.
- Created all front-end templates ensuring consistent display of content across multiple browsers and operating systems (Mac OS X, Windows, Android, Chromebook, iOS, Firefox, Chrome, Safari, etc.)
- Designed and built experimental "technology enhanced" assessment items and mini-assessments such as drag-anddrop, reorder, text editing, fill-in-the-blanks, audio playback and recording, etc.
- Utilized BrowserStack and VMWare Fusion to ensure compatibility and consistency across multiple operating systems and browsers.
- » Utilized Mac VoiceOver, NVDA, and JAWS to ensure screen reader compatibility for features and item types.
- Created semantic HTML, ARIA tagging to ensure WCAG 2.0 AA conformance.
- Worked with accessibility specialists to provide further improvements to usability and accessibility.
- » Developed interactive prototypes with HTML/CSS/Javascript.

Freelance - Lawrence, KS 2006-now |

Web/graphic designer, full-stack web developer, photographer

- » Worked with business owners and stakeholders to gather business requirements, create design briefs, and manage
- Designed websites, logos, print collateral.
- Worked with clients and stakeholders to design page layouts, site architecture, and interface elements for various websites.
- Built websites and web applications on top of existing content management systems.
- Created standards-based, semantic front-end templates to implement designs consistently across a multitude of different browsers and operating systems.
- Photographed products and interiors.
- Created front-end templates for websites to ensure consistent display of content across multiple browsers and operating systems (Mac OS X, Windows, Android, Chromebook, iOS, Firefox, Chrome, Safari, etc.)
- Integrated designs with user-friendly content management systems and created documentation to train clients to manage their own websites and content.
- » Created custom scripts to integrate content from APIs into custom content management systems.
- » Integrated content management systems into Facebook and XBOX APIs.
- » Created and maintained an anonymous web-based online voting system.

Education

University of Kansas - Lawrence, KS United States

Bachelor's Degree 05/2006

Major: Visual Communications (Graphic Design)

Tools

- Graphic Design: Photoshop, Illustrator, InDesign
- Wireframing/Prototyping: Adobe XD, Sketch, Axure, OmniGraffle, OmniOutliner, OmniPlan
- » Front End: HTML5, HAML, CSS3, SASS/LESS, Javascript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Foundation
- » Back End: Ruby on Rails, PHP, JSON, MySQL
- » Version Control: Git
- » Content Mangement: ExpressionEngine, WordPress, Joomla, Drupal
- IDE: RubyMine (Jetbrains), Panic Coda, Panic Nova, Sublime Text, WebStorm
- Documentation and Collaboration: Slack, Microsoft Teams, Microsoft Office (Word, Excel), Asana